Guide to the Bacon-Schneeloch Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Bacon-Schneeloch family papers
1875-1935
MS 707
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
6.5
(9 boxes)
The papers consist of family correspondence, autograph albums, diaries, notebooks, financial records, photographs and memorabilia, principally of Leonard Woolsey Bacon, a physician, and of his first wife, Emma Waleska Schneeloch. The largest part of the papers is made up of Bacon's prescription books (1892-1937) containing diagnosis, prescriptions, and name, age and occupation for each patient. Also in the papers are the financial records of his practice (1907-1919) which, together with the prescription books, make an important record of the practice of medicine in New Haven in that period. In the family correspondence is a long series of letters (1886-1892) from Leonard Bacon to Emma Schneeloch during their courtship. Much of the correspondence is made up of letters from various members of the Bacon family who were opposed to the marriage. Emma Schneeloch sang with her sister, Emilie, with a band that traveled to the West in 1891. A diary kept by Emilie of this trip is in the papers. Also included are student papers from Vassar (ca. 1917-1921) and other memorabilia kept by Emma Waleska Bacon Evans, daughter of Leonard and Emma Bacon.
Bacon family
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. Leonard W. Bacon, 1939.
Biographical / Historical
LEONARD WOOLSEY BACON, 1865-1939, B.A. 1888.
Born February 24, 1865, in Stamford, Conn.
Died January 8, 1939, in Hamden, Conn.
Father, Rev. Leonard Woolsey Bacon (B.A. 1850, M.D. 1856, D.D. 1879). Mother, Susan (Bacon) Bacon. Yale relatives include: Leonard Bacon (B.A. 1820) (grandfather); Benjamin W. Bacon (B.A. 1847), Theodore Bacon (B.A. 1853), Francis Bacon (M.D. 1853), George B. Bacon (B.A. 1856), Edward W. Bacon (B.D. 1869), Thomas R. Bacon, '72, Alfred T. Bacon, '73 (uncles); Henry S. Bacon, '93, Leonard B. Smith, '94, Winthrop D. Smith, '96, Leonard` B. Bacon, '96, Harrison Gray, ex-'oo S., Roger T. Bacon, ex-'II S., Alfred H. T. Bacon, '14, Henry W. Closson, '16, Agnes B. Sargent, '24 Art (cousins); Leonard Bacon, '09, B. Selden Bacon, '11, Wallace G. Corwin, 'I7, Selden D. Bacon, '31, Nathanael B. Greene, '31 S. (nephews); Dorothy B. Woolsey, ex-'09 Art, Margaret T. Corwin, M.A. Hon. 1934 (nieces).
Norwich Free Academy, The Bingham School, Asheville, N.C., and Phillips-Andover. Attended Amherst College 1884-1885. Entered Yale in 1885; third English composition prize Sophomore year; dissertation appointment Junior year; a founder of the Yale Orchestra and its librarian Junior year; member Andover Club.
Attended University of Leipzig 1887-1888, University of Pennsylvania 1888, Syracuse University 1889, and Mills Training School for Male Nurses, Bellevue School of Nursing, 1889-1890; worked as professional nurse in Europe and United States 1889-91; attended Yale School of Medicine 1891-1892 (M.D. 1892); postgraduate study of medicine at universities of Tübingen and Bern 1906-1907; engaged in practice of medicine New Haven 1892-1918, and since 1923; specialized in general surgery and orthopedics; assistant medical clinic Yale University School of Medicine 1892-1894 and surgical clinic 1895-1897; instructor operative surgery 1897-1905 and surgery 1905-1906; city physician 1893-1894; member of staff Hospital of St. Raphael and Grace Hospital; commissioned Major, Medical Corps, September 5, 1918; attended Medical Officers' Training Camp, Camp Greenleaf; assigned to General Hospital No. 3; on orthopedic service Children's Hospital and Massachusetts General Hospital; assistant chief and later chief of orthopedic service General Hospital No. 32, Chicago, February 1-June 15, 1919; surgeon chief General Hospital No. 16, New Haven, June 15, 1919, until discharge September 1, 1919; in U.S. Public Health Service in charge of surgical staff Hospital No. 41, 1919-1923; contributed numerous articles to medical and scientific journals; a founder of Beaumont Medical Club; president American Society of Orthopedic Surgeons, and New Haven Medical Association 1908; vice-president Connecticut State Medical Society 1935-1936; first vice-president Association of Yale Alumni in Medicine 1924-1925 and president 1925-1926; member New Haven County and American Medical associations, and New Haven Colony Historical Society.
Married (1) July 6, 1892, in New Haven, Emma Waleska, daughter of Hugo and Emilie (Neumann) Schneeloch, and sister of Ralph H. Schneeloch, ex-'01 M. Children: Leonard Woolsey, Jr., ex-'17; and Emma Waleska (B.A. Vassar 1921), the wife of Theodore Schlosser Evans, '17 (M.D. Columbia 1921). Mrs. Bacon died July 17, 1925. Married (2) April 8, 1927, in Bridgeport, Conn., Esther Louise, daughter of William and Anna Oleson. Children: Thorwald Oleson; Susan Esther; and Theodare Davenport.
Death due to coronary occlusion. Buried in Grove Street Cemetery, New Haven. Survived by wife, children, one grandchild, four sisters, Margaret B. Corwin, the wife of Robert N. Corwin, '87, Miss Susan Almira Bacon (B.A. Mount Holyoke College 1905; Ph.D. Yale 1911), of Palo Alto, Calif., Mabel Bacon Ripley (B.A. Smith College 1896), wife of Philip F. Ripley, '97, and Elizabeth Bacon Greene, the wife of Prescott M. Greene, '03 S., a brother, Selden Bacon, ex-'83, and a half brother, David Leonard Bacon, '16 S. His brothers, Nathaniel T. Bacon, '79 S., Benjamin W. Bacon, '81, and Theodore D. Bacon, '83 S., died in 1926, 1932, and 1930 respectively.
Dr. Bacon willed his prescription stubs to the University Library "as an authentic record of the actual practice of a New Haven physician."
YALE UNIVERSITY Obituary Record, 1938-1939, pp. 59-60.
Scope and Contents
The Bacon-Schneeloch Family Papers consist mainly of correspondence and miscellaneous papers of Leonard Woolsey Bacon, Jr. (1865-1939); his wife, Emma Waleska (Schneeloch) Bacon (1862-1925); and their parents, brothers and sisters, and other close relations. Series I, CORRESPONDENCE, spans from 1875 to 1935, but the letters are concentrated in the period of Leonard's and Emma's courtship, 1887 to 1892, and the Bacon family's opposition to their marriage is a primary theme. The principal correspondents are Leonard Woolsey Bacon (1830-1907), writing to his son and his future daughter-in-law, and Leonard Woolsey Bacon (1865-1939), writing to his future wife. Besides the Bacon family correspondence, there are letters to the Schneeloch family from friends and relations in New York, New Jersey, and Germany.
Series II, OTHER PAPERS, contains autograph albums, diaries, academic papers, documents, photographs, drawings, and printed memorabilia. The Schneeloch sisters [Emma Waleska (Schneeloch) Bacon and Emilie Auguste (Schneeloch) Busse] are represented by autograph albums beginning in the early 1880s and diaries from their tour with Gilmore's Band in 1891. For Leonard Woolsey Bacon, Jr., there are school papers, an autograph album, and monthly summaries of the financial status of his medical practice. The papers of his daughter, Emma Waleska (Bacon) Evans, are mainly from her student days at Vassar. Hardly any of the photographs are identified, but most are probably of Schneeloch relations in New York and New Jersey.
The Music Library has a separate collection of Schneeloch Papers, consisting mainly of programs and clippings from the sisters' appearances as singers. The register of that collection is available in this department.
There is a Bacon family tree in the register of the Bacon Family Papers, Manuscript Group No. 46.
Courtship; Emigration and immigration; Families; Medicine -- Formulae, receipts, prescriptions; Medicine -- Connecticut -- New Haven; Music; Europe; Germany; New Haven (Conn.); West (U.S.); Clergy; Singers; Physicians; Autographs (manuscripts); Diaries; Bacon, Emma Waleska Schneeloch, 1862-1925; Bacon, Leonard Woolsey, 1830-1907; Bacon, Leonard Woolsey, 1865-1939; Bacon, Susan Almira, 1869-1946; Bacon, Susan Bacon, 1835-1887; Busse, Emilie Auguste Schneeloch; Dwight, Timothy, 1828-1916; Evans, Emma Waleska Bacon, 1897-; Evans, Waleska Bacon, 1923-; Schneeloch family; Schneeloch, Emilie Elisabeth Neumann
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1875-1935; Series I
  - Bacon, Benjamin Wisner (1860-1932), to LWB, 1890, 1892, 1906-1907 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
    Leonard Woolsey Bacon (1865-1939)
  - Bacon, Eliza Buckingham (Selden), to EWSB, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Emma Waleska (Schneeloch) Bacon (1862-1925)
  - Bacon, Emma Waleska (Schneeloch) (1862-1925), to
    - Eliza Buckingham (Selden) Bacon, [1891] (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Helen (Hazard) Bacon, [1890] (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Leonard Woolsey Bacon (1830-1907), 1890 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Emma Waleska (Bacon) Evans (1897-), 1925 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Waleska Bacon Evans (1923-), 1925 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Richard Hackett, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bacon, Frances J. (Mills), to LWB, 1888 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bacon, Helen (Hazard) (1861-1925), to
    - EWSB, [1890] (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - LWB, 1885 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bacon, Leonard Woolsey (1830-1907), to
    - EWSB, 1887 September-1892 April (Box 1, Folder 12-14)
    - LWB, 1878-1892 (Box 1, Folder 15-25)
  - Bacon, Leonard Woolsey (1865-1939), to
    - Benjamin Wisner Bacon (1860-1932), 1892 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - EWSB, 1886-1890 (Box 1, Folder 27-42)
    - EWSB (cont'd), 1891-1906 (Box 2, Folder 43-54)
    - Leonard Woolsey Bacon (1830-1907), undated (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Selden Bacon (1861-), 1891 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - ________ Brant, 1890 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Emilie Auguste (Schneeloch) Busse ([1867?]-), 1887 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Martha Jane (Schneeloch) Munson (1871-), 1891 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Emma Waleska (Bacon) Evans (1897-), 1903 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - Leonard Woolsey Bacon (1894-), 1903 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - Julius Hawley Seelye (1824-1895), 1884 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Unidentified incoming letters, 1883-1890 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Bacon, Leonard Woolsey (1865-1939), and Emma Waleska (Schneeloch) Bacon (1862-1925), to "bird-readers", 1893 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Bacon, Letitia Wilson (Jordan), to LWB, 1890 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Bacon, Nathaniel Terry (1858-1926), to LWB, 1878, 1885-1890, 1906-1907 (Box 2, Folder 64-65)
  - Bacon, Selden (1861-) to LWB, 1884, 1890, 1892 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Bacon, Susan (Bacon) (1835-), to LWB, 1877-1883 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Bacon, Susan Almira (1869-1946), to LWB, 1883-1889, undated (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Bacon, Theodore (1834-1900), to LWB, 1890 (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Bacon, Theodore Davenport (1863-), to LWB, 1883-1890 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Bacon, Thomas Rutherford (1850-1913), to LWB, 1892 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Bacon sisters to LWB, undated (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Bancroft, F.P., to LWB, 1884 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Bingham, Major Robert, to LWB, 1883 (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - Carrington, Sarah, to LWB, undated (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - Corwin, Margaret Wardell (Bacon) (1866-), to
    - EWSB, 1891 (Box 2, Folder 76)
    - LWB, 1878-1889, undated (Box 2, Folder 77)
  - Dwight, Timothy (1828-1916), to LWB, 1887 (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - Evans family, 1921, 1931-1935 (Box 2, Folder 79)
  - Foster, Ernest A., to LWB, 1883-1886 (Box 2, Folder 80)
  - Greene, Elizabeth Rogers (Bacon) (1881-), to LWB, 1889-1890, undated (Box 2, Folder 81)
  - Little, Arthur M., to LWB, 1884-1885 (Box 2, Folder 82)
  - Neumann family to Schneeloch family, 1911, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 83)
  - Oertel, Hanns (1868-), to LWB, 1922 (Box 2, Folder 84)
  - Ripley, Mabel Ginevra (Bacon) (1874-), to LWB, 1883, 1890 (Box 2, Folder 85)
  - Schneeloch, Emilie Elisabeth (Neumann) (1841- 1905), to EWSB and Emilie Auguste (Schneeloch) Busse ([1867?]-), 1887, 1891-1892 (Box 2, Folder 86)
  - Schneeloch, Hugo (1837-) to
    - EWSB and Emilie Auguste (Schneeloch) Busse ([1867?]-), 1876, 1887, 1891 (Box 2, Folder 87)
    - [EWSB and LWB?], 1906 (Box 2, Folder 88)
  - Schneeloch friends and relations in Germany to Bacon-Schneeloch family, 1892-1926, undated (Box 2, Folder 89)
  - Sumner, E. Stewart, to EWSB, 1889 (Box 2, Folder 90)
  - Tilton, W.H., to LWB, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 91)
  - Wallner, Eugene, to
    - EWSB, undated (Box 2, Folder 92)
    - LWB, 1883-1890, undated (Box 2, Folder 93-96)
  - Wallner, Julia, to LWB, 1876, 1886-1891 (Box 2, Folder 97)
  - Wardell, Margaret, to LWB, 1875, 1890 (Box 2, Folder 98)
- OTHER PAPERS, 1855-1935; Series II
  - Bacon, Emma Waleska (Schneeloch) (1862-1925)
    - Autograph albums, with illustrations, 1881-1888, 1891-1892, 1906 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - "List of Wedding Announcements" and marriage certificate, 1892 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Notebook of social calls, 1896, 1910 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Note on the nature of music, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Bacon, Leonard Woolsey (1865-1939)
    - Academic certificates, 1876-1889 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Autograph album, 1880, 1883 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Catalogue of the Bingham School and leaflet, 1883, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous papers from his stay in Germany, 1887-1888 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Financial records of medical practice, 1907-1919 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - "English Examination: The Cotter's Saturday Night", undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Busse, Emilie Auguste (Schneeloch) ([1867?]-)
    - Autograph album, with illustrations, 1880-1894 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Diaries of western trip with Gilmore's Band, 1891 October-December (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Evans, Emma Waleska (Bacon) (1897-)
    - Themes and other student papers, Circa 1917-1921 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - "Yale 1920" name tag (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Notebook in social psychology, 1920 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - "Her Book - 1923 - Jottings and Bits of Nothing" (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Scrapbook containing printed cutouts for children, undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Evans, Waleska Bacon (1923-): diary, 1935 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Schneeloch, Hugo: birth certificate (copy), 1882 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Schneeloch, Otto: draft letter and notes re his design for a revolver chamber for firearms, 1872 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Schneeloch family: genealogical notes, undated (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Certificate of ownership of three gravesites in the Evergreens Cemetery, Brooklyn, 1866 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Notebook, loose notes, and menu from European travel, 1906 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Unidentified writings in German, undated (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Miscellaneous papers, undated (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Business and calling cards, undated (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Ornamental box containing autographs and calling cards from Germany and printed mementoes in German and English, 1855, undated (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Newspaper clippings, undated (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Printed memorabilia, undated (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Photographs (unidentified, but more Schneeloch than Bacon), undated (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Drawings, undated (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Doll's clothing, undated (Box 4, Folder 32)
- Additional Material, 1892-1937; Accession 1981-M-004
  - Prescription books containing diagnosis, prescriptions, name, age, and occupation of the patient. (Box 1–5)